John Roberts Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
John Roberts Papers
1881 - 1991
1946 - 1950
npkmc-2212-091
John Roberts (1914 - 2006)
1 Linear foot 2 Boxes 37 Folders
John Roberts was born on March 16, 1914, in Massachusetts. During World War II, John was assigned to the Signal Corps Photo Center on Long Island. Once discharged, John was sent to the Near East by Lowell Thomas to make a complete film for the Near East College Association. In 1948, John covered the Winter Olympics and met Clayton Ballou, who would be his business partner for the next 50 years. Together they released a 30-minute color short of Andrea Mead Lawrence, and titled it “Born to Ski”. John also worked on several assignments for Lowell Thomas in Persia, Tibet, Calcutta, Bangkok, Hong Kong, Macaoe, Japan, Hawaii, and Alaska. In 1954, Clayton Ballou and John Roberts formed Associated Film Producers Inc., and produced 19 travel documentaries and commercials. This collection consists of materials created or saved by John Roberts and contains documents from his trip to the Middle East on behalf of Lowell Thomas, the correspondence of John Roberts, and materials from the production of travel films, including film proposals, scene outlines, film scripts, and the associated promotional materials, programs, and booklets. There are also a significant number of photographs in this collection.
Marist College Archives and Special Collections 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie, NY Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
There are no restrictions on this collection
John Roberts was born on March 16, 1914, in Massachusetts. From an early age, he took an interest in the production of motion pictures and started taking 16mm films as a hobby when he was 15 years old. After high school and preparatory school, at his father’s suggestion, John worked an office job at the United Shoe Machinery Corporation. He worked here for over three years, but eventually chose to quit to concentrate on making films. He started showing his films to small clubs, usually for free, and doing paid videography work, such as weddings. In the late 1930s, John took up an interest in making ski films and made several advertising films for New England resorts. When the war came along, John was assigned to the Signal Corps Photo Center on Long Island, where he completed the basic course in motion picture. He was then sent to Wright Field to help make training films for the Air Force. During this time, John had the opportunity to work in the camera department, rear projection, sound, and eventually in production. Eventually, John was assigned as a motion picture instructor at the training school, where he served out his army time. Once discharged, John was sent to the Near East by Lowell Thomas to make a complete 16mm film for the Near East College Association. This project culminated in a one-hour film that was narrated by Lowell Thomas. In 1948, John went to Switzerland to cover the Winter Olympics and to make a ski film, where John met Clayton Ballou, who assisted John in the editing of the film. They worked as a team from that point forward. In 1950, John and Clayton travelled West to cover seven of the Major ski areas for another ski film. The film was well received, but they decided that the market for ski films was too limited, and they gave up making ski pictures. Being unknown and with no capital, John and Clayton struggled to get work. But they continued and began to experiment doing their own sound using a Magnacorder. It was around this time that they put together a 30-minute color short of Andrea Mead Lawrence, and titled it “Born to Ski”. After the success of “Born to Ski”, John and Clayton started on a television series titles, “American Profiles”. They completed 13 episodes that were 13-minute life-story capsules of interesting people. But with the quick growth of television, Clayton and John were not able to keep up. While producing “American Profiles’, John also worked on several assignments for Lowell Thomas. He spent several months with Lowell Thomas, Jr. in Persia, and then joined with Lowell Thomas Sr. for the first leg of their trip into Tibet. But John did not get a permit to enter Lahasa, so he returned to the United States through the Pacific so he could make films for Lowell Thomas in Calcutta, Bangkok, Hong Kong, Macaoe, Japan, and Hawaii. The following year, John went with Lowell Thomas Sr. to Alaska to film the work of the Juneau Icecap Research Project. In 1954, Clayton Ballou and John Roberts produced the full-length 16mm Cinemascope film for the lecture field called “Filmorama Adventure”. Filmorama road-showed with a lecturer coast to coast and was a great success. After the success of Filmorama, Clayton and John decided to make several more similar shows, adding live sound and interviews. Together, they formed Associated Film Producers Inc., and made their first film on New England, titled “This is New England”. They went on to make 18 more travel documentaries and produced commercials.
This collection consists of materials created or saved by John Roberts and contains documents from his trip to the Middle East on behalf of Lowell Thomas. Materials from the Middle East Trip include scrapbook pages, a journal, and correspondence from the trip. This collection also contains the correspondence of John Roberts, advertisements he worked on, newspaper clippings, biographical notes and obituaries for John Roberts, and materials from the production of travel films, including film proposals, scene outlines, film scripts, and the associated promotional materials, programs, and booklets. There are also a significant number of photographs in this collection, including photographs of Lowell Thomas and from various trips taken by Lowell Thomas, photographs taken over the course of his career, personal photographs of John Roberts and friends, and photographs from vacations.
Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981; Thomas, Lowell, 1923-2016; Lawrence, Andrea Mead; Ballou, Clayton (1923-2010); Roberts, John (1914-2006); Associated Film Producers; Tibet Region; Photography; Skis and skiing--History; Travelogues (Motion pictures); Alaska; Middle East; Switzerland; Netherlands
This collection is organized into seven series: 1) Middle East Trip, 2) Correspondence, 3) Travel Film Production Materials, 4) Published Materials, 5) Personal Materials, 6) Photographs, contains three subseries, 6.1) Photos of Lowell Thomas, 6.2) Photographs from Career, 6.3) Personal Photographs, and 7) Miscellany.
Collection was donated to Marist College Archives & Special Collection by Phillip Wales, who obtained the collection from the Roberts family.
No accruals are expected.
Lowell Thomas Papers: Textual Materials
Lowell Thomas Papers: Graphic Materials
Lowell Thomas Film Collection
- 1. Middle East Trip, 1946 - 1947
  Series contains a transcription of the “journal” that John Roberts mailed home to his father describing the day-to-day experience of the trip, items saved as souvenirs from the trip, many of the items are pasted onto cardstock for a scrapbook, and correspondence related to the trip to the Middle East, some letters and telegrams have been pasted onto cardstock and were a part of the scrap book.
  - Journal, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typewritten Journal Pages, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harry R. Snyder on behalf of John Roberts to New York Customs regarding project for Near East College Association, March 28, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Albert W. Staub on behalf of John Roberts regarding project for Near East College Association. Includes newspaper clipping, The Observant Citizen, Boston Post, May 6, 1946, March 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lowell Thomas to John Roberts, regarding project for Near East College Association, April 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Father of John Roberts to John Roberts. Includes a middle eas airlines luggage tag, April 26, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Allen Baily, Near East College Association, May 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Father of John Roberts to John Roberts., May 8, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ralph L., American School for Boys, Baghdad, Iraq to John Roberts, May 8, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Father of John Roberts to John Roberts., May 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - S.E. Kerr, Acting Dean, American University of Beirut, to John Roberts, Includes two tickets., May 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lowell Thomas to John Roberts, May 20, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Father of John Roberts to John Roberts., May 20, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lowell Thomas to John Roberts, May 20, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ralph, Fund for Near East Colleges to John Roberts, May 26, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Father of John Roberts to John Roberts, May 28, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ralph L., American School for Boys, Baghdad, Iraq to John Roberts (opposite side has a visa from the Swiss consulate), May 30, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Stewart, American University Beyrouth (Telegram), June 18, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Allen M. Bailey to John Roberts, June 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Allen Bailey, June 23, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Miss Mihailova, June 27, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Lowell Thomas, June 23, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - George B. Stewart to John Roberts, June 25, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to Allen Bailey, June 27, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - George B. Stewart on behalf of John Roberts to the Lebanese Customs, June 25, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Telegram, July 12, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Telegram from John Roberts, June 27, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - George B, Stewart to John Roberts, July 7, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Telegrams, July 18, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to his father, July 27, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to his father, July 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lowell Thomas to John Roberts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cable, John Roberts to Lee Terrill, YMCA, Jerusalem, July 21, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cable, John Roberts to Mary Davis, New York, July 30, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mary Davis, Secretary to Lowell Thomas, to John Roberts, August 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Telegrams, August 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to his father, August 11, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Roberts to his father, August 15, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Allen M. Bailey to Mr. and Mrs. A.J. Roberts, August 30, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harry H. Vaughn, Major General, U.S. Army, Military Aide to the President, to Allen Bailey (copy), June 24, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter of Recommendation for John Roberts from Lowell Thomas (Original and copy), August 6, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter of Recommendation for John Roberts from William Paton, American Director of Near East College Association (Original and copy), October 22, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Server Iskit (in Arabic), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Card with Eagle Seal, in Arabic, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Card with Eagle Seal, in Arabic, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Middle East Scrapbook Pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Vulcania Postcard (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Postcard, Napoli - Panorama (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Luggage tag for United States Lines, August 22, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Luggage Tag, The USA War Shipping Administration (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Luggage Tag, Air France (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Luggage Tags, Trava LTD (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Landing Card, S.S. Vulcania (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Luggage Tag, Middle East Airlines (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ticket, Transcontinental and Western Air (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Shepheard's Hotel, Vairo, Dinner Menu, July 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert College, Alumni Banquet Menu, June 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Orient Palace Hotel, Lunch menu, May 15, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American University of Beirut Commencement Exercises Ticket and Invitation, June 26, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cartoon, Road to Morocco (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Inoculations list, January 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Medications list for John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Recipe (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Education: Where East is West, TIME, September 9,1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Vulcantan clipping, April 1, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clipping, Sports of the Times by Arthur Daley (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Program of the Military Review (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ceremonial program of the national day (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Program of the second day (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 2. Correspondence, 1948 - 1991
  Series contains correspondence between Clay Ballou and John Roberts, Lowell Thomas, postcards to the wife of John Roberts, and other correspondence, including government communications. In addition, the series contains the journal entries John Roberts would mail home as part of his letters to his father or friends.
  - Clay Ballou's Letters to John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Envelope addressed to John Roberts, August 18, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Envelope addressed to John Roberts, December 13, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, November 21, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clay Ballou to John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John Roberts Letters to Clay Ballou (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Roberts to Clay Ballou, August 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Roberts to Clay Ballou, Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Roberts to Clay Ballou, September 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Roberts to Clay Ballou, September 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Roberts to Clay Ballou, June 19, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Journal pages mailed to Clay Ballou, spans June 14 through August 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Postcard, John Roberts to Clay Ballou, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Postcards, 1957 - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jeanne and Harry E. to John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, August 18, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, May 22, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, June 1, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, June 11, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, June 15, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, June 1, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, June 1, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, July 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, July 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, July 24, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, July 30, 19963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, August 8, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, August 16, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, December 13, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Roberts to Mrs. A.J. Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Switzerland Correspondence and Journal, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, January 12, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, January 12, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, January 17, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, January 20 - 29,1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, January 30 - February 4, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, February 05 - 07, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, February 02 - 10, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, February 12 - 20, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, February 23 - 29, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 1 - 3, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 5-12, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 13 - 19, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 20 - 22, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 22 - 28, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, March 29 - 30, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - John Roberts to his father, April 3, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - John Roberts to his father, April 7, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages mailed to John Robert's Father, includes a small note, April 8 - 11, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - John's father to John Roberts, includes copy of letter to Mary Davis, April 13, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - to John, April 14, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Telegraph receipt to Arthur Roberts, 1948-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal pages, April 18 - 24, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Other correspondence, 1958 - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harry H. Vaughn, Major General, U.S. Army, Military Aide to the President, to Allen Bailey (copy), June 24, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hannes Schneider about ASSIGNMENT SWITZERLAND, March 1, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Swiss National Tourist Office to John Roberts, November 20, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Swiss National Tourist Office to John Roberts, November 28, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From the Netherlands Information Service, March 29, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Roberts to Favid G. Dodwell, October 25, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Roberts to ANdrea Mead Lawrence (copy), January 5, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From Janet Mead, President of Pico Peak, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Roberts to David G. Dodwell (copy), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Roberts to Al, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 3. Travel Film Production Materials, 1947
  Series contains materials related to the production of travel films. This includes film proposals, scene outlines, a script for the “Near East” film production, promotional materials for the travel programs, and travel film booklets.
  - Film Proposals (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Prospectus for a 16mm cikir film for the travel lecture field in charge of production: John Roberts and Clayton Ballou. Associated Film Producers (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Born to ski (revised) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scene Outlines (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Caribbean Paradise" filmed by John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, presented and narrated in person by John Roberts. Martin A. Forrest (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Denmark and the Danes" filmed by John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, narrated by John Roberts. Martin A. Forrest (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Highlights of New England" filmed by John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, narrated by John Roberts. Martin A. Forrest (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Holland and the Amazing Dutch" filmed by John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, narrated by John Roberts. Martin A. Forrest (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Holland and the Amazing Dutch" scene list (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Switzerland Unlimited" filmed by John Roberts and Clayton Ballou, narrated by John Roberts. The Handley Management (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Switzerland today" scene list (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Valley of the Rhine" scene list (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Near East Film Script (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Near East Film Script (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Travel Program Promotional Materials (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Jon Roberts presents "Magnificent Austria" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Westward Ski" with Andy Mead, Alf Engen, Lowell Thomas. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Westward Ski" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Near East College Association presents "Outposts of American Education". First Showing, Barbizon Plaza Theatre (3), May 27, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Near East College Association presents "Outposts of American Education". New England Tour, Summer, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Near East College Association presents "Outposts of American Education". Produced by John W. Roberts, Described by Lowell Thomas, Edited by John Primi (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Roberts presents "Puerto Rico" (x2) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Norway by John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "A New Norway" and "Carribbean Paradise" by John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "A New Norway" and "Carribbean Paradise" by John Roberts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Clayton Ballou and John Roberts presents "Switzerland Today" (copy) (Box 1, Folder 13)